<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-27T20:18:10-05:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ramblings</title><subtitle>Hoi</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Structured Prediction Pt. 1 - Linear-chain CRF</title><link href="/jekyll/update/2021/01/25/crfpt1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Structured Prediction Pt. 1 - Linear-chain CRF" /><published>2021-01-25T13:09:17-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-25T13:09:17-05:00</updated><id>/jekyll/update/2021/01/25/crfpt1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll/update/2021/01/25/crfpt1.html">&lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re looking at part 1 of a series of posts about &lt;em&gt;structured prediction with conditional random fields&lt;/em&gt;. In this post, we’ll talk about linear-chain
CRFs applied to POS tagging. It will cover the necessary background to understand the motivation behind using a CRF,
talking about things like &lt;em&gt;discriminative and generative modeling&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;probabilistic graphical models&lt;/em&gt;, training a linear-chain CRF
with efficient inference methods using &lt;em&gt;dynamic programming&lt;/em&gt; like &lt;em&gt;belief propagation&lt;/em&gt; (AKA the forward-backward algorithm), and decoding with &lt;em&gt;Viterbi&lt;/em&gt;. In part 2, 
we will implement all these ingredients in the popular deep learning library &lt;a href=&quot;https://pytorch.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PyTorch&lt;/a&gt;.
If you want to skip the background and start implementing, go to &lt;a href=&quot;/jekyll/update/2021/01/25/part2.html&quot;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;.
Part 3 and 4 of this series will go into using more general (non-linear) CRFs for dependency parsing. OK! Let’s start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following sentence that is partly annotated with part-of-speech tags (POS tags):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/annotated_example.gif&quot; alt=&quot;annotated_example&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether the POS-tag we want to continue the labeling process with here is a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;noun&lt;/code&gt; or a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;verb&lt;/code&gt; depends on the POS-tag of the previous
 word. In this case the previous label is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;determiner&lt;/code&gt;, so we want to choose &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;noun&lt;/code&gt;. 
 For sequence labeling tasks like this, and more general for structured prediction tasks, it is helpful to
jointly decode the sequence, keeping into account dependencies among the labels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;structured-prediction&quot;&gt;Structured Prediction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structured prediction is a framework for solving problems of classification or regression in which the output variables
are mutually dependent or constrained. It can be seen as a subset of prediction where we make use of the structure in
the output space. The loss function used in structured prediction problems considers the outputs as a whole, meaning in
the example above the loss of a sequence that has a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;verb&lt;/code&gt; following a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;determiner&lt;/code&gt; will be higher than a sequence where
 a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;noun&lt;/code&gt; follows a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;determiner&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s denote the input sequence of words by \(\mathbf{x}\), the output space (i.e., the set of all possible target sequences) 
by \(\mathcal{Y}\) and \(f(\mathbf{x}, \mathbf{y})\) some function that expresses how well \(\mathbf{x}\) fits 
\(\mathbf{y}\) (we will clarify what this function is later), then prediction can be denoted by the following formula:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\mathbf{y}^{\star} = arg \max_{\mathbf{y} \in \mathcal{Y}} f(\mathbf{x}, \mathbf{y})\]

&lt;p&gt;The disctinction between regular classification and structured prediction is that for the latter some kind of
search needs to be done over the output space – finding the \(\mathbf{y} \in \mathcal{Y}\) that maximizes the
function \(f(\mathbf{x}, \mathbf{y})\). An exhaustive search is usually intractable and structured
prediction methods, like conditional random fields, are required. To see why, consider that if we let the number of possible
POS-tags be \(|\mathcal{S}|\) and the sequence length \(m\), there are \(|\mathcal{S}|^m\) possible sequences we would need to search over.
Note that if we would ignore the dependencies in the output space and simply proceed decoding ‘greedily’, we could use the following formula for prediction
for all words in the input sequence separately, requiring only \(|\mathcal{S}|\cdot m\) operations:&lt;/p&gt;

\[y_i^{\star} = arg \max_{y \in \mathcal{S}} f(\mathbf{x}, y_i, i) \text{ for } i \in \{1, \dots, m\}\]

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conditional-random-field&quot;&gt;Conditional Random Field&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A conditional random field (CRF, &lt;a href=&quot;https://repository.upenn.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1162&amp;amp;context=cis_papers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Lafferty et al., 2001&lt;/a&gt;) is a probabilistic graphical model that combines advantages of &lt;em&gt;discriminative classification&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;graphical models&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;discriminative-vs-generative-models&quot;&gt;Discriminative vs. Generative models&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the discriminative approach to classification we model \(p(y \mid x)\) directly as opposed to the generative case 
where we model \(p(x \mid y)\) and use it together with Bayes’ rule for prediction. If we model the conditional
 directly, dependencies among \(x\) itself play no rule, resulting in a much simpler inference problem than modeling
  the joint \(p(y, x)\). Generative models describe how some label \(y\) can generate some feature vector \(x\), whereas
   discriminative models directly describe how to assign a feature vector \(x\) a label \(y\). CRFs are discriminative models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;graphical-models&quot;&gt;Graphical Models&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probabilistic graphical models (PGMs) represent complex distributions over many variables as a product of local factors of smaller subsets of variables. 
Based on what kind of graphical structure (i.e., conditional independence assumptions) one assumes, one can use linear 
chain CRFs or more general CRFs. Generative models are often most naturally represented by directed graphical models (models \(p(x,y) = p(y)p(x \mid y)\)), whereas
discriminative models are most naturally represented by undirected graphical models (models \(p(y \mid x)\) directly). 
See in the figure below a generative PGM on the left, and a discriminative on the right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gen_vs_discr_pgm.png&quot; alt=&quot;pgms&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRFs can be represented as &lt;em&gt;factor graphs&lt;/em&gt;. A factor graph is a graph \(G = (V,F,E)\), in which \(V\) denotes the random 
variables, \(F\) denotes the factors,
and \(E\) the edges. A factor graph describes how a complex probability distribution factorizes, and thus imposes independence relations. 
A distribution \(p(\mathbf{y})\) factorizes according to a factor graph \(G\) if there exists a set of local functions \(\psi_a\)
such that \(p\) can be written as:&lt;/p&gt;

\[p(\mathbf{y}) = \frac{1}{Z} \prod_{a \in F} \psi_a(y_{N(a)})\]

&lt;p&gt;The factors \(\psi_a\) are each only dependent on the neighbors \(y_i\) of \(a\) (denoted by \(y_{N(a)}\)) in the factor graph.
The factors need to be larger than zero, but need not have a probabilistic interpretation. The trick in using a factor graph
for a task like classification is defining a set of feature functions that are nonzero only for a single class. Luckily, 
we don’t need to hand-engineer such feature functions anymore and can hit it with the DL hammer &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;:)&lt;/code&gt; (which we will cover in &lt;a href=&quot;/jekyll/update/2021/01/25/part2.html&quot;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt; of this series).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;linear-chain-crf&quot;&gt;Linear-Chain CRF&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it’s time to design a CRF for POS-tagging. We will use the fact that we want the prediction for each tag \(y_i\) to
depend on both the previously predicted tag \(y_{i-1}\) and the input sequence of words \(\mathbf{x}\). This gives us the following factor graph:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/lincrf.png&quot; alt=&quot;lincrf&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graphical model underlying this particular linear-chain CRF implies two conditional independence assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each POS-tag is only dependent on its immediate predecessor and \(\mathbf{x}\): \(y_t \mathrel{\unicode{x2AEB}} \{y_1, \dots, y_{t - 2}\} \mid y_{t - 1}, \mathbf{x}\)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each word in the sentence \(x_t\) only depends on the current POS-tag \(y_t\): \(x_t \mathrel{\unicode{x2AEB}} \{x_i\}_{i \neq t}, \{y_i\}_{i \neq t} \mid y_t, \mathbf{x}\).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can simply multiply all the factors in the above factor graph to get our the factorizied conditional probability distribution:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{aligned}
p(\mathbf{y} \mid \mathbf{x}) &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{Z(\mathbf{x})} \prod_{t=1}^{m} \psi(y_t, \mathbf{x}, t) \prod_{t=1}^{m-1}\psi(y_t, y_{t+1}) \\
 \end{aligned}\]

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, what you need to know about a CRF is that it’s simply a specific way of choosing the factors, or in other
words feature functions. The CRF-way of defining the factors is taking an exponential and a linear combination of 
real-valued feature functions \(f(\cdot)\) with parameters \(\boldsymbol{\theta}_1\) and \(\boldsymbol{\theta}_2\):&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{aligned}
p(\mathbf{y} \mid \mathbf{x}) &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{Z(\mathbf{x})} \prod_{t=1}^{m} \exp\left(\boldsymbol{\theta}_1 \cdot f(y_t, \mathbf{x}, t)\right)\prod_{t=1}^{m-1} \exp\left(\boldsymbol{\theta}_2 \cdot f(y_t, y_{t+1})\right) \\ 
  &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{Z(\mathbf{x})} \exp\left(\sum_{t=1}^m \boldsymbol{\theta}_1 \cdot f(y_t, \mathbf{x}, t) + \sum_{t=1}^{m-1} \boldsymbol{\theta}_2 \cdot f(y_t, y_{t+1})\right) \\
Z(\mathbf{x}) &amp;amp;= \sum_{\mathbf{y}^{\prime}}\exp\left(\sum_{t=1}^m \boldsymbol{\theta}_1 \cdot f(y^{\prime}_t, \mathbf{x}, t) + \sum_{t=1}^{m-1} \boldsymbol{\theta}_2 \cdot f(y^{\prime}_t, y^{\prime}_{t+1})\right)
 \end{aligned}\]

&lt;p&gt;Intuitively, the first sum in the exponent above represents the probabilities that a particular \(y_t\) is the right POS-tag at time \(t\), and the
second sum represents the probabilities that each \(y_{t+1}\) follows a particular \(y_{t}\). The value \(Z(\mathbf{x})\) is
just the partition function ensuring that this formula is a properly defined probability distribution that sums to 1. Again, here the sum over all
possible sequences of \(\mathbf{y}\) appears, and naive methods of computing this sum are intractable, which is why we will use belief propagation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;training-a-linear-chain-crf&quot;&gt;Training a Linear-Chain CRF&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can train the CRF with regular maximum likehood estimation, given a set of \(N\) datapoints. Performing gradient 
descent over the likelihood will require computing the factors from the PGM, which can be efficiently found with probabilistic
inference methods like belief propagation. Let’s take a look at the log-likelihood:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{aligned}
\log \mathcal{L}(\boldsymbol{\theta}) &amp;amp;= \log{\prod_{i=1}^N p(\mathbf{y}^{(i)} \mid \mathbf{x}^{(i)}, \boldsymbol{\theta}) } =  \log{\Bigg[\prod_{i=1}^N \frac{1}{Z(\mathbf{x}^{(i)})}\prod_{t=1}^m \psi_t (y_t^{(i)}, \mathbf{x}_t^{(i)}, t) \prod_{t=1}^{m-1} \psi_t (y_t^{(i)}, y_{t+1}^{(i)}) \Bigg]} \\
    &amp;amp;=  \log{\Bigg[\prod_{i=1}^N \frac{1}{Z(\mathbf{x}^{(i)})} \exp\Bigg\{\sum_{t=1}^m \boldsymbol{\theta}_1 f_t(y_t^{(i)}, \mathbf{x}_t^{(i)}, t) + \sum_{t=1}^{m-1} \boldsymbol{\theta}_2 f_t(y_t^{(i)}, y_{t+1}^{(i)})\Bigg\}\Bigg]} \\
    &amp;amp;= \log{\Bigg[\prod_{i=1}^N \exp\Bigg\{\sum_{t=1}^m \boldsymbol{\theta}_1 f_t(y_t^{(i)}, \mathbf{x}_t^{(i)}, t) + \sum_{t=1}^{m-1} \boldsymbol{\theta}_2 f_t(y_t^{(i)}, y_{t+1}^{(i)})\Bigg\}\Bigg]} + \log{\Bigg[\prod_{i=1}^N \frac{1}{Z(\mathbf{x}^{(i)})} \Bigg]} \\
    &amp;amp;= \sum_{i=1}^{N}\sum_{t=1}^m \boldsymbol{\theta}_1 f_t(y_t^{(i)}, \mathbf{x}_t^{(i)}, t) + \sum_{t=1}^{m-1} \boldsymbol{\theta}_2 f_t(y_t^{(i)}, y_{t+1}^{(i)}) - \sum_{i=1}^{N}\log\left(Z(\mathbf{x}^{(i)})\right) \\
\end{aligned}\]

&lt;p&gt;To optimize the parameters, we need to calculate the gradients of the log-likelihood w.r.t. the parameters:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{aligned}
\nabla_{\boldsymbol{\theta}_1} \log \mathcal{L}(\boldsymbol{\theta}) &amp;amp;= \sum_{i=1}^{N}\sum_{t=1}^m f_t(y_t^{(i)}, \mathbf{x}_t^{(i)}, t) - \sum_{i=1}^N \nabla_{\boldsymbol{\theta}_1} \log(Z(\mathbf{x}^{(i)}))  \\
\nabla_{\boldsymbol{\theta}_1} \log(Z(\mathbf{x}^{(i)})) &amp;amp;= \frac{\nabla_{\boldsymbol{\theta}_1}Z(\mathbf{x}^{(i)})}{Z(\mathbf{x}^{(i)})} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{\sum_{\mathbf{y}^{\prime}}\exp\left(\sum_{t=1}^m \boldsymbol{\theta}_1 \cdot f(y^{\prime}_t, \mathbf{x}, t) + \sum_{t=1}^{m-1} \boldsymbol{\theta}_2 \cdot f(y^{\prime}_t, y^{\prime}_{t+1})\right) \cdot f(y_t^{\prime},\mathbf{x},t)}{Z(\mathbf{x}^{(i)})} \\
&amp;amp;= \sum_{y_1^{\prime}}\dots\sum_{y_m^{\prime}} p(\mathbf{y} \mid \mathbf{x})  \cdot f(y_t^{\prime},\mathbf{x},t) \\
&amp;amp;= \sum_{y^{\prime}_t} p(y_t \mid \mathbf{x})  \cdot f(y_t^{\prime},\mathbf{x},t)
\end{aligned}\]

&lt;p&gt;Where the last step is true because we simply marginalize out all \(y_i\)’s for which \(i \neq t\). Similarly for the gradient w.r.t. \(\boldsymbol{\theta}_2\):&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{aligned}
\nabla_{\boldsymbol{\theta}_2} \log \mathcal{L}(\boldsymbol{\theta}) &amp;amp;= \sum_{y^{\prime}_t}\sum_{y^{\prime}_{t+1}} p(y_t,y_{t+1} \mid \mathbf{x})  \cdot f(y_t^{\prime},y_{t+1}^{\prime})
\end{aligned}\]

&lt;p&gt;This shows that for the backward pass over the CRF computations we need the marginals \(p(y_t \mid \mathbf{x})\) and \(p(y_t,y_{t+1} \mid \mathbf{x})\),
which we can again compute efficiently with belief propagation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;efficient-inference-with-belief-propagation&quot;&gt;Efficient Inference with Belief Propagation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For inference we simply need to calculate the function for \(p(\mathbf{y} \mid \mathbf{x})\) for a given input sequence.
The nominator is easy to compute, but the denominator requires summing over all possible target sequences, which is intractable.
Belief propagation (BP) is an algorithm to do efficient inference in PGMs, and we can use it to get the exponential time for
computing the partition function down to polynomial time. Additionally, to calculate the gradients of the log-likelihood w.r.t. the parameters, 
 we need to calculate the marginals. We’ll also use BP for this, but it’s easiest to explain if we first go over how to 
  use it to calculate the partition function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall that, if done naively, the complexity of computing the
 partition function is \(|S|^m\). With some dynamic programming magic we can get this down to \(m \cdot |S|^2\). 
 How this works can be illustrated well when we write out the sums in the partition function 
 (for the sake of this illustration we will use the factors \(\psi(\cdot)\) again):&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{aligned}
Z(\mathbf{x}) &amp;amp;= \sum_{\mathbf{y}^{\prime}}\left(\prod_{t=1}^m \psi(y^{\prime}_t, \mathbf{x}, t) \cdot \prod_{t=1}^{m-1} \psi(y^{\prime}_t, y^{\prime}_{t+1})\right) \\
&amp;amp;= \sum_{y^{\prime}_1}\sum_{y^{\prime}_2}\dots\sum_{y^{\prime}_m}\psi(y^{\prime}_1, \mathbf{x}, 1) \cdot \dots \cdot  \psi(y^{\prime}_m, \mathbf{x}, m) \cdot  \psi(y^{\prime}_1, y^{\prime}_{2}) \cdot  \dots \cdot  \psi(y^{\prime}_{m-1}, y^{\prime}_{m})
\end{aligned}\]

&lt;p&gt;Now if we rearrange the sums and take each factor as far forward as possible we get:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{aligned}
Z(\mathbf{x}) &amp;amp;= \sum_{y^{\prime}_m}\psi(y^{\prime}_m, \mathbf{x}, m)\sum_{y^{\prime}_{m-1}}\psi(y^{\prime}_{m-1}, \mathbf{x}, m-1)\psi(y^{\prime}_{m-1}, y^{\prime}_{m}) \dots \dots \\ 
&amp;amp; \quad \quad \quad \dots \sum_{y^{\prime}_2}\psi(y^{\prime}_2, \mathbf{x}, 2) \cdot  \psi(y^{\prime}_2, y^{\prime}_{3})\underbrace{\sum_{y^{\prime}_1}\psi(y^{\prime}_1, \mathbf{x}, 1) \cdot  \psi(y^{\prime}_1, y^{\prime}_{2})}_{\alpha(1, y^{\prime}_{2})}
\end{aligned}\]

&lt;p&gt;If we look at the last sum in the above equation, we can view it as a function of \(y^{\prime}_2\): \(\alpha(1, y^{\prime}_2)\),
which for each value of \(y^{\prime}_2\) returns the sum over all \(y_1^{\prime}\):&lt;/p&gt;

\[\alpha(1, y^{\prime}_2) = \sum_{y^{\prime}_1}\psi(y^{\prime}_1, \mathbf{x}, 1) \cdot  \psi(y^{\prime}_1, y^{\prime}_{2})\]

&lt;p&gt;This function can also be seen as a vector of size \(|S|\) (that’s how many values \(y^{\prime}_2\) can take), where each entry
represents a sum over, again, \(|S|\) values of \(y^{\prime}_1\) (now we can start to see where the \(|S|^2\) term in the time complexity comes from).
 We can compute these and use them for the next sum in the equation. Let’s make this a bit clearer with an image. The below
 image shows the flow of computation in a the DP algorithm belief-propagation. The columns are steps over time (from 1 to \(m-1\)),
 and the rows are all different values \(y^{\prime}\) can take, which in this case are the POS-tags. So the vector representing \(\alpha(1, y^{\prime}_2)\) 
 in the image below is the first column of green boxes. Then for all next time steps we can use the following recursion:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\alpha(t, y^{\prime}_{t+1}) \leftarrow \sum_{y^{\prime}_{t}}\psi(y^{\prime}_t, \mathbf{x}, t) \cdot  \psi(y^{\prime}_t, y^{\prime}_{t+1})\cdot \alpha(t-1, y^{\prime}_t)\]

&lt;p&gt;So for each green box in the image below, we compute the above recursive function that uses all green boxes from the previous column. This costs
 \(|S|\) operations for one green box, and we do this for each green box, in total \(|S|^2\) times. We do this for each column, giving us \((m-2) \cdot |S|^2\) operations.
 If we then also consider the initialization computation for \(\alpha(1, y^{\prime}_2)\) costing \(|S|^2\) operations we get
 the complexity of \((m - 1) \cdot |S|^2\). And then we just need to calculate the partition function from this, costing another \(|S|^2\) operations (see text below image).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/beliefprop.png&quot; alt=&quot;beliefprop&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By computing all the column vectors, we can finally get the partition function as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

\[Z(\mathbf{x}) = \sum_{y^{\prime}_m}\psi(y^{\prime}_m, \mathbf{x}, m) \cdot\alpha(m-1, y^{\prime}_m)\]

&lt;p&gt;Where \(\alpha(m-1, y^{\prime}_m)\) are the values of the rightmost column. And, we get to the final complexity of \(m \cdot |S|^2\) for computing the partition function. If this is all we wanted,
we would be done now. However we also need the marginals for calculating the gradient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From probability theory we know that computing the marginals from a joint means summing (in the discrete case) over 
all other variables, to marginalize them out. We need both \(p(y_t \mid \mathbf{x})\) and \(p(y_t, y_{t+1} \mid \mathbf{x})\):&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{aligned}
p(y_t \mid \mathbf{x}) &amp;amp;= \sum_{y_1}\dots\sum_{y_{t-1}}\sum_{y_{t+1}}\dots\sum_{y_m}p(\mathbf{y} \mid \mathbf{x}) \\
p(y_t, y_{t+1} \mid \mathbf{x}) &amp;amp;= \sum_{y_1}\dots\sum_{y_{t-1}}\sum_{y_{t+2}}\dots\sum_{y_m}p(\mathbf{y} \mid \mathbf{x})
\end{aligned}\]

&lt;p&gt;In the previous we saw how to compute this sum if we were to sum over all \(y_t\)’s, but we can also
use it also to compute the marginals. To this end, we first do the exact same
as before to calculate the partition function, but rearranging the sums in a different way:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{aligned}
Z(\mathbf{x}) &amp;amp;= \sum_{y^{\prime}_1}\psi(y^{\prime}_1, \mathbf{x}, 1)\sum_{y^{\prime}_{2}}\psi(y^{\prime}_{2}, \mathbf{x}, 2)\psi(y^{\prime}_{1}, y^{\prime}_{2}) \dots \dots \\ 
&amp;amp; \quad \quad \quad \dots \sum_{y^{\prime}_{m-1}}\psi(y^{\prime}_{m-1}, \mathbf{x}, m-1) \cdot  \psi(y^{\prime}_{m-1}, y^{\prime}_{m-2})\underbrace{\sum_{y^{\prime}_m}\psi(y^{\prime}_m, \mathbf{x}, m) \cdot  \psi(y^{\prime}_{m-1}, y^{\prime}_{m})}_{\beta(m, y^{\prime}_{m-1})}
\end{aligned}\]

&lt;p&gt;Now, by similar argument as the forward-case, we can do DP as illustrated by the following image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/beliefprop_backward.png&quot; alt=&quot;beliefprop_backward&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can calculate the rightmost column as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\beta(m, y^{\prime}_{m-1}) = \sum_{y^{\prime}_m}\psi(y^{\prime}_m, \mathbf{x}, m) \cdot  \psi(y^{\prime}_{m}, y^{\prime}_{m-2})\]

&lt;p&gt;Then, going backward from timestep \(m-1\) to timestep 2, we can compute the following recursion:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\beta(t, y^{\prime}_{t-1}) \leftarrow \sum_{y^{\prime}_{t}}\psi(y^{\prime}_t, \mathbf{x}, t) \cdot  \psi(y^{\prime}_t, y^{\prime}_{t-1})\cdot \beta(t+1, y^{\prime}_t)\]

&lt;p&gt;We can combine the &lt;em&gt;forward&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;backward&lt;/em&gt; way of calculating the partition function to calculate the marginals. To see how, rearrange all the terms in the marginal:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{aligned}
p(y_t \mid \mathbf{x}) &amp;amp;= \sum_{y_1}\dots\sum_{y_{t-1}}\sum_{y_{t+1}}\dots\sum_{y_m}p(\mathbf{y} \mid \mathbf{x}) \\
&amp;amp;\propto \underbrace{\sum_{y_{t-1}}\psi(y_{t-1},\mathbf{x}, t-1)\sum_{y-2}\psi(y_{t-2},\mathbf{x}, t-2)\psi(y_{t-2},y_{t-1}) \dots \sum_{y_1}\psi(y_{1},\mathbf{x}, 1)\psi(y_{1},y_{2})}_{\alpha(t-1, y_t)} ...\\
&amp;amp; \dots \underbrace{\sum_{y_{t+1}}\psi(y_{t+1},\mathbf{x}, t+1)\sum_{y_{t+2}}\psi(y_{t+2},\mathbf{x}, t+2)\psi(y_{t+2},y_{t+1}) \dots \sum_{y^{\prime}_m}\psi(y^{\prime}_m, \mathbf{x}, m) \cdot  \psi(y^{\prime}_{m-1}, y^{\prime}_{m})}_{\beta(t+1, y_t)}  \\
&amp;amp; \quad \quad \cdot \psi(y_t, \mathbf{x}, t) \\
&amp;amp;\propto \alpha(t-1, y_t) \cdot \beta(t+1, y_t) \cdot \psi(y_t, \mathbf{x}, t)
\end{aligned}\]

&lt;p&gt;Note that we ignored the normalization constant in the above (hence the \(\propto\) sign), and we still need to normalize to get our marginal probability:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{aligned}
p(y_t \mid \mathbf{x}) &amp;amp;= \frac{\alpha(t-1, y_t) \cdot \beta(t+1, y_t) \cdot \psi(y_t, \mathbf{x}, t)}{\sum_{y^{\prime}_t}\alpha(t-1, y{\prime}_t) \cdot \beta(t+1, y{\prime}_t) \cdot \psi(y{\prime}_t, \mathbf{x}, t)}
\end{aligned}\]

&lt;p&gt;By similar reasoning:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{aligned}
p(y_t, y_{t+1} \mid \mathbf{x}) = \frac{\alpha(t-1, y_t) \cdot \beta(t+2, y_{t+1}) \cdot \psi(y_t, \mathbf{x}, t) \cdot \psi(y_t, y_{t+1}) \cdot \psi(y_{t+1})}{\sum_{y^{\prime}_t}\sum_{y^{\prime}_{t+1}}\alpha(t-1, y_t^{\prime}) \cdot \beta(t+2, y_{t+1}^{\prime}) \cdot \psi(y_t^{\prime}, \mathbf{x}, t) \cdot \psi(y^{\prime}_t, y^{\prime}_{t+1}) \cdot \psi(y^{\prime}_{t+1})}
\end{aligned}\]

&lt;p&gt;Now we have everything we need for the forward pass, inference, and the backward pass of gradient descent on the log-likelihood!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;viterbi-decoding&quot;&gt;Viterbi Decoding&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that’s left to discuss before we can start implementing is how to decode – meaning finding the maximum scoring target sequence according to our model. 
This amounts to solving the following equation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\(\mathbf{y}^{\star} = arg\max_{\mathbf{y} \in \mathcal{Y}} p(\mathbf{y} \mid \mathbf{x})\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources-i-used-for-this-post&quot;&gt;Sources I used for this post&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following sources I heavily used for this post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://repository.upenn.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1162&amp;amp;context=cis_papers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The original CRF paper&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;John D. Lafferty, Andrew McCallum, and Fernando C. N. Pereira. Conditional random fields: Probabilistic models for segmenting and labeling sequence data. In Proceedings of the Eighteenth International Conference on Machine Learning, ICML ’01, pages 282–289, San Francisco, CA,USA, 2001. Morgan Kaufmann Publishers Inc.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The absolutely awesome &lt;a href=&quot;https://homepages.inf.ed.ac.uk/csutton/publications/crftutv2.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;introduction to CRFs&lt;/a&gt; by Charles Sutton and Andrew McCallum. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Charles Sutton and Andrew McCallum. An introduction to conditional random fields. Found.Trends Mach. Learn., 4(4):267–373, April 2012.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugo Larochelle’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GF3iSJkgPbA&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;tutorial on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;. Clearest explanation to be found about CRFs afaik!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Structured Prediction Pt. 2 - Implementing a linear-chain CRF</title><link href="/jekyll/update/2021/01/25/part2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Structured Prediction Pt. 2 - Implementing a linear-chain CRF" /><published>2021-01-25T13:09:17-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-25T13:09:17-05:00</updated><id>/jekyll/update/2021/01/25/part2</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll/update/2021/01/25/part2.html">&lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hoi&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, %s&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Tom'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>